你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到高级利用
welcome back to advanced exploitation
PWN学院的组合模块的第二个视频
the second putting it all together module of pwn college
今天专门讨论通过堆上的竞争条件进行数据泄露
today we're going to be talking about data disclosure via race conditions on the heap specifically
我们这里使用上个视频末尾提到的服务
as a reminder we have our example service here from the previous video
它有很多安全检查
the service has a lot of security checks
但是这些安全检查
but these security checks
尽管它们在单线程场景中很好
while they are good in a single threaded scenario
但在多线程场景中是差强人意的
are bad in a multi threaded scenario
所以我们要迈出开发利用的第一步
so we're going to kind of take the first step toward exploitation
这里也有一个微不足道的缓冲区溢出
there's also a trivial buffer overflow here
在fscanf到栈上的input变量时
in this fscanf onto the input variable on the stack
但我们无法利用它
but we can't exploit that of course
因为我们不知道金丝雀，也不知道任何地址
because we don't know the canary or any addresses
好吧
all right
让我们深入了解一下
so let's dive in
我们有很多
we have a lot of
这是一个多线程服务
this is a multi threading service right
我们可以连接到它
we can connect to it
每个连接都在自己的线程中运行刚刚看到的循环
and each connection gets its own thread to run through that loop that we just saw
当然，正如从竞争条件模块中知道的那样
of course as you know from the race condition module
当多个线程同时运行时，危险就可能发生
with multiple threads going on at the same time crazy stuff can happen
结论是程序中的代码可以以任何顺序执行
the takeaway is all of the this code that is in the original program can really run in any order
因为你能让足够多的线程做不同的事
because you can get enough threads in there doing a lot of different stuff
而且线程之间的执行顺序是交错的
that execution ordering between threads gets interleaved
但它们都基于全局变量执行
and they all act on global data
因此，一个线程修改全局变量，其他线程也会受到影响
and so when one thread modifies global data that effect is seen in the other thread as well
因此，启动足够多的线程，灵活地编织它们的行为
so by interleaving in a clever way with enough threads actions in this program
你可以以任何顺执行这些依赖全局变量的指令
you can basically run any of this stuff in more or less any order with the global data being acted upon
这有几个要注意的
and there are a couple of things here
我们能用一个线程将任意一个全局消息设置成已存或未存状态
one is we can have one thread set the stored or unstored condition of any of the global messages
同时用另一个线程打印消息，或分配消息内存
while another thread is printing them out or another thread is allocating
或者我们可以在消息释放后，重新分配前，打印它（uaf）
or we can have a print triggered after a free before an allocation
即使在代码中它是做了保护的
even though in the normal code it's guarded
因为我们可以在其他线程中设置stored[idx]为0或1
because we can trigger these stored indexes yes and stored indexes no in other threads
所以我们可以利用竞争条件绕过这些防护
we can basically bypass these guards with race conditions
这里的核心概念是
the core concept here is that
在单线程场景中有用的安全检查
you can have security checks that makes sense in a single threaded scenario
如果你不考虑到每一个攻击场景
and if you don't specifically think about every attack scenario
如果你没考虑多线程场景
if you don't specifically think about the multi threaded case
而你的库或程序最终被以多线程的方式使用
and your library your program ends up being used in a multi threaded way
这些安全检查是不够的
those checks can be insufficient
好吧，让我们来看看具体细节
alright let's take a look at you know specifics
刚刚讲的有点抽象了
I know this is a little high level
让我们来看看可以拆解出来的
but let's take a look at a specific way in which this can break down
利用这个程序的具体步骤
from the perspective of accomplishing some actual step toward exploitation this program
好的，我们很接近了
right so we're close right
在babyheap中有和现在相同的功能
as in babyheap you had the same sort of primitives
比如malloc scanf free
you had malloc scanf free
当时是puts，现在是printf
instead of printf you had puts
老实说，都差不多
it's the same thing honestly
所有这些工具
and all of these tools
你用了这些工具来利用babyheap
you used all these tools to achieve exploitation in babyheap
但现在缺少必要信息
but here we don't know where anything is
和某个babyheap中的场景一样
like a scenario that you face in babyheap
不知道PIE基址
you don't know where the PIE base is
不知道ASLR后的基址，比如库的基址
we don't know where the ASLR base is for a library address and stuff
不知道栈基址，堆基址
we don't know where the stack is the heap base
还有栈金丝雀
the canary right
如果我们知道金丝雀和libc基址，就可以ROP
if we knew the canary and let's say the libc base  we could ROP
或者知道PIE基址，也可以ROP
or the PIE base we could ROP
正如从babyrop中学到的
as you know from babyrop
但我们不知道金丝雀
but we don't know the canary
这些基址我们都不知道
we don't know any of those bases
从babyheap中知道了，能用这些功能泄露地址
so from babyheap as you know you can use these primitives to start disclosing addresses
比如你可以用tcache来
so for example you could use tcache to
通过使用这些竞争条件
by using these race conditions
和穿插执行不同指令的能力
and the ability to interleave different instructions all at the same time
基本上能复现在babyheap中做的事
you can accomplish basically what you did with babyheap
比如先释放消息
in terms of triggering a free of a message
然后再打印消息
and then triggering a print of that message right
这是可行的
and that is a viable path forward
但有个问题
there's one complication
事情并不像你想象的那么简单
things aren't as simple as you might expect
在babyheap中，我们研究了单线程程序中的堆
so in babyheap we looked at heap operations in a single threaded program
单线程程序有一个主线程
a single threaded program has one main thread
但ptmalloc，t表示线程
and it turns out that ptmalloc which stands for P thread malloc
实际上使用了很多多线程概念
actually has a lot of thread specific concepts that it employs
其中之一是arenas（竞技场）
one of these concepts is arenas
它放弃了一些旧有想法
going off of the idea that
如，不同线程往往做不同的事
different threads tend to do different things
线程间分享的资源往往比线程内用的要少等等
tend to share fewer resources between threads than they do within that thread and so forth
ptmalloc为每个线程提供自己的arena，数量有限超了共用
ptmalloc had the bright idea to give every thread kind of its own heap
宏观上的堆实际上被分成了多个arena
so the heap is actually split into arenas
每个arena都能被进程中的线程访问到（链表相连，有锁）
each arena lives in a section of memory accessible to all the threads in the process
每个arena都记录了一片内存用来分配chunk
but each arena has a space for its chunks that that arena will allocate
还有指向其它arena的指针
and pointers back to other arenas in case that arena runs out of space and so forth right
线程至少会从一个arena中取过内存
each thread ends up with at least one arena to allocate from
因为ptmalloc的算法
I think actually there's some crazy algorithm by which
一个线程可能在8还是几个arena中取过chunk
a thread might end up with up to 8 arenas or some amount of arenas
但要知道的是
but basically the takeaway is
在非主线程中malloc获得的地址
that the addresses that you receive from malloc within a non main thread
和主线程中malloc获得的地址不同
are different than the addresses you receive from malloc within the main thread
这意味着
this means that
1泄露出的指针指向的是普通线程的arena
one the leaks will be pointers to the threads arena
而不是
instead of the
这个应该是1
this is this should be one probably
稍等，我改一下
let me just fix that and slide 1 sec
好了
all right
现在要点的顺序没问题了
now you have the takeaways in the proper order
第一个要点是
so the first takeaway is
当有信息泄露，也许是堆误用导致的
the leaks that you might get out of a heap misuse
比如泄露了tcache的next指针
the tcache forward pointer leak
它将会是一个指向普通线程arena的指针
is going to be a pointer to the threads arena
（口误发现中）
是一个指向普通线程arena中的chunk的指针
a pointer to a chunk in the threads arena
指向的是arena中的某个地址
to somewhere inside it
第二条：这些线程的头几个chunk的地址含有00
and then two early chunks in those threads will have nulls in the addresses
让我们来看看为什么会这样
let's take a look at why this is
为了探究这个概念
to explore that specific concept
我写了个arena.c
I created arena.c
一个非常简单的多线程程序
we have basically a very simple multi-thread program
它启动了一堆线程
that spins up a bunch of threads
每个线程只是malloc一次，请求大小和前面讲的例子相同
and just does one malloc and the same size malloc as in our example program
编译一下
so let's compile this
运行一下
here we go let's run it
让我
and actually let me
刚意识到，在主arena中也这样做，会更好
just realized it would be good to also do this in the main arena
有了主线程的结果
so we have the main thread
这很像我们在babyheap中习惯的
this looks like a heap address that you're used to from babyheap
接着是一堆我们没想到会从malloc返回的地址
and then here are a bunch of different weird addresses that you don't expect from malloc
能看到它们都以B60结尾
and you can see they're all end in this B60
显然有一些
so obviously there is some
如果我们把它改成2个malloc 16
if we modify this to have two malloc of 16
让我们，是的
and let's yeah
它们当然会交织在一起，但是
they're gonna get interleaved of course but
看到了
here we see it
它从0x60增加到0x80
it goes from hex 60 to hex 80
增加的这个是chunk的大小
which of course is the size of the chunk
它有可用大小16字节（0x10）
that has a usable allocation space of 16 bytes
还有0x10字节用来放chunk元数据
right there's the extra hex 10 for the chunk metadata
但基本上
but basically
它们都是在不同高内存区的低地址处
these are all at very similar low addresses in different high address allocation areas
当线程启动时
basically when the thread starts up
libc会为它分配一个arena
libc allocates an arena for it
来响应malloc请求
to service malloc requests
它基本上是特定于线程的
so basically this is a thread specific
也不能说是特定于某个线程（线程过多会共用）
well not quite thread specific
只能说是为了这个线程创建的一片堆
but a piece of the heap creates specifically for the thread
当然，它在线程外也有效
of course it is valid outside of the thread
实际上，如果用strace -f，你能看到创建它的过程
and you can actually see it being created  if you do strace -f
举个例子，我们从这里找一个
for example let's grab one of these
这个
this guy
它是刚刚的堆地址之一
it's one of the heap addresses
看看它是从哪里来的
and let's see where that came from
在这里
there
这是在用mprotect设置堆
so this is the mprotect setting up that heap
这是，额，unmap??
here's the uh unmap
这是,
here's that
抱歉，这是。
sorry this is a
再多过滤一个字节
let's grab more oh an extra byte
1 2 3 4 5 6好的
1 2 3 4 5 6 yeah
这应该足以避免混淆
that should be enough to avoid confusion
筛出来的太多了
I think you're seeing way too many
额
ah it it um
这就是不按剧本来的后果
this is what happens when you go off script
我觉得它是在别的地方分配的
I think it gets allocated elsewhere
或者有可能是通过其它隐式方法创建的
or rather by by something else implicitly possibly
不，这些都不是
nope these are all
啊，在这里
ah here here is
好了，开始吧
okay here we go
我们有这个地址
we have this address
7f932c0
let's say 7f932c0
这里的某个地方应该在分配它
and then somewhere here we're going to be allocating
这儿，7 f 9 32 c 0....
boom 7 f 9 3 2 c 0 blah blah blah
它来自以7结尾的PID，就是这个
this is from PID ending in 7 that's this guy
所以在线程创建后的某一刻
so at some point after creation it actually
线程首次使用malloc时，libc会为该线程分配一个arena
libc will allocate an arena for this thread when it first goes to use the heap
好的
all right whoops
这用另一个方法，验证了
that was a roundabout way of saying that threads have
说明由线程分配的地址通常
allocated addresses by a thread will often
但并非总是，这取决于堆缓存的状态等等
but not always it really depends on the state of the heap cache and everything
通常是特定于线程的
often have end up with addresses that are kind of thread specific
当然要记住一点
now of course keep in mind
这让我们发现一个待掌握的新知识点——线程相关的arena
so this first of all gives us a new thing that we need to know the thread specific arenas
但请记住，这不是个什么全新的内存区
but keep in mind this isn't removed like independently existing somewhere in memory
只是个内存映射
this is memory map
一个处在某种程度上由内核决定的地址的内存映射
memory map at an address that is decided by the Linux kernel at least to some extent
它们之间还是相互有些关联的
I think at the very least they're very relative to each other
如果你泄露了一个，剩下的你也就知道了
I think if you leak one you know the rest
将来我们会看到如何从一个泄露的arena，了解到更多内存信息
but we'll see how to go from leaking one to knowing much more of the memory space
总之，线程arena的泄露途径很广
all right anyways so we have thread specific arenas that we can leak on top of everything
我们继续深入
so let's dive in
（纠正前面口误，略）
that we can leak on top of everything
我们现在讨论的信息泄露
so now our information disclosure that we talked about
它利用程序的并发问题泄露tcache指针
with this tcache pointer leak to carry out in this program that has concurrency errors
能提供一个线程arena地址（但null导致打印不全）
will at first give us a thread specific arena address
该如何解决打印不全的问题呢
so how do we do it all right
有2种方法
we have two routes first we can use race conditions to
方法1，利用提供的malloc，分配大量内存
or just intelligent use of those message allocations to make enough allocations
使后续获得的内存地址中不含空字节
to create an address that doesn't have null bytes in it
如果我们分配足够多的内存
right so if we allocate enough messages
最终
then eventually
malloc返回的地址中的空字节
that single null byte that we were seeing in the address of the the return of malloc
将会消失
will go away
它会以1开头
it'll become a 1 initial
显然，随着分配次数增多，地址会增长
and then obviously keep climbing as more and more is allocated
这样就解决了这个问题
and then we'll be able to beat this
我们可以这样做
we can take that route
我们还可以用另一个有趣的方法
we can also take a different route that's very interesting
稍微变通一下竞争条件的利用方法
we can utilize the same race condition in a slightly different context
欺骗一下另一处代码
to confuse a different part of the code
这个代码甚至不在我们写的程序中
that's not even in the program
它在库里
that's in the libraries
想一下printf是如何实现的
so consider how printf is implemented
在我们的代码中，输出时调用了
in our code we have this in the printf functionality of
fprintf "message:%s" stored[idx]
fprintf message column percent s of  the stored index right
printf是如何实现的
how is printf implemented
你会如何实现它
how would you implement it
你要往一个文件中写入一个字符串
you need to write to some file descriptor a string
但是事先不知道要写入的字符串
but that string isn't known ahead of time
具体来说，事先不知道要写入字符串的长度
the length of the string more specifically isn't known ahead of time
需要先解析要写入的长度
you need to parse the length to write in that
然后printf会调用write
and then printf will call write
所以它首先需要算出字符串的长度
so it first needs to figure out the length of the string
然后再写入
and then it does the write
你会发现，在我们这个例子中
and you notice something in our kind of strawman example
我们没有对字符串占用的内存加锁
we didn't lock the memory that the string is occupying
也没有办法这样加锁
there is no way to just lock memory like that anyways
如果加锁的话，我们需要一个互斥锁
right we would need a mutex
所有这个字符串的使用者
everyone that uses that string
都得同意在使用字符串前先上互斥锁
would have to agree that before they touch the string they lock the mutex
printf使用时要上互斥锁、
and then printf would lock the mutex
算长度、写入、解锁
do the length do the write unlock the mutex
这不是不可行
this is not non viable
因为
because
只是开发者一般不会这么做
just developers won't do that
你从没想过
you never think about
哦，printf前我该上个锁
oh I should lock this mutex when I do printf and so forth
实际上，这就是printf
so realistically speaking this is printf
而且我们可以与其竞争
and we can race printf
想象一下
so imagine this
先malloc分配内存
you use the malloc action to allocate memory
再scanf填充大量可打印的非空数据
then you use the scanf action to fill it with some large amount of printable not null data
然后将它打印出来
then when you go to print it out
此时printf会解析它的长度
printf will take its length
当然，你希望在此时竞争成功
and then of course this is where you hope to win the race
需要在strlen之后，write之前，切换到另一个线程
you win the race by having the other thread get scheduled between the strlen and the write
然后
and then fill the
那叫什么来着
ah what's it called
哦，抱歉，然后在那个线程free它
oh sorry and then free that allocation
free时，libc会写入堆元数据
of course then libc will pthread will write in the pthread metadata when it frees the allocation
write将按原长度，输出free时写入的元数据
and your write will actually write out the pthread metadata of that length
很疯狂，但确实有效
pretty crazy right but it actually works
事实上，这里竞争成功并不困难
in fact this is not a hard race to win
因为write是一个系统调用
because write is a system call
所以这个线程会暂停，然后跳转到内核
and this thread will basically pause to jump into the kernel
内核会做一些检查
the kernel will do some checks
可能还要去执行别的进程或线程
might go execute something else
具体要看调度策略和当时的环境
depending on the scheduling policy and what else has been going on
与此同时，另一个线程在不同的核心上运行
in the meantime this other thread is running on a different core
并释放这个内存
and free that allocation
而且这里没有互斥锁
and there are no mutexes anywhere
互斥锁是要显式声明的
you know the mutexes are something that you have to do explicitly
我们看看具体该如何利用
let's take a look at how to exploit this
这是我们这个程序表面的第一个裂缝
this is our first kind of crack in the veneer of this program
哦，不，我刚刚显示界面有问题
oh no I switched to the wrong thing okay
这个是我刚才在讲的ppt
here's that slide that I was just talking about
刚刚放在右上角了，看起来很小
that was tiny on the top right alright cool
我们继续
let's dive onwards
现在在终端
so here is our terminal
我创建了这个ult程序
I created the program as this ult
ult启动了
so ult is now running
我可以连接到 localhost 1337
I can connect to localhost 1337
连上了
and here it is
它提供了 malloc scanf printf
malloc scanf printf
我可以malloc 1
I can malloc allocation 1
scanf 1
scanf allocation 1
输入 hello
say hello
printf  1
printf allocation 1
输出 hello
and it says hello
这样我们就能，还记得堆的利用技巧吗
so that we， remember our heap trickery
我可以连接
I can connect
重来吧
let's just restart this whole thing
好的
all right
接入
connect up
可以 malloc 0 malloc 1 malloc 2
I can say malloc an allocation 0 malloc an allocation 1 malloc an allocation 2
再 free 0 free 1 free 2
of course I can free allocation 0 free allocation 1 free allocation 2 and now
现在如果我打印的话应该可以
I should be able to if I printf
不好意思，如果我malloc，会拿到最后释放的chunk
oh sorry if I then malloc whatever the last thing that was freed
所以chunk3的地址是
so allocation 3 is now gonna be
chunk3的地址是
that pointer could be put into allocation
是原来缓存在tcache中的chunk2
the pointer that was in allocation 3 is going to be returned again by tcache to allocation 2
如果我执行printf
if I do printf here
可能是不可显字符（没指定内存，等待输入中）
it's probably not printable
我们这样试一下
so let's do this
退出
let's quit
确实打印了message:
so it did give me message colon
然后
then
3a，不，3a是冒号
3a no 3a is the colon
啊，好了
ah here we go
不是，是空格
nope space
zero
啊，是的，这个是30 13
ah yeah here we go 3 0 13
这是泄露地址的最后两字节
that is the last two bytes
我好奇它为什么需要
I wonder why it needed
我们再来一次
let's just do this again
我复制一下
let me copy that
里面包含了一堆换行符
including a bunch of new lines
nc认为它
so that Netcat realizes it's
好了，我们开始吧
okay there we go all right here we go when we say
输出了message:空格
it says message colon space
30 13 换行符
3 0 1 3 new line right
如果我们少malloc一个
if we have one fewer allocation
末尾的地址应该不同
it'll be a different last bytes
只显示末尾地址，是因为小端序和00阻断了printf
with that null byte as we talked about is screwing us up
还是30 13
still 3 0 1 3
为什么是30 13
why why 3 0 1 3
哦
oops
我的锅
my bad
这应该是printf 3
that should be printf three
我message呢?
where's my message
肯定是io相关缓冲区问题
there's some buffering problem for sure
我们在Python中试试
let's do this in Python
执行malloc 0 malloc 1 free 0 free 1 malloc 3 printf 3 quit
okay we're gonna do malloc 0 malloc 1 free 0 free 1 malloc 3 printf 3 quit
然后打印出所有内容
and then we're going to print everything
好了
all right there we go
message是0x30 0x13
message is hex 30 Hex 13
如果我们多malloc一个
if we do an additional allocation instead
比方说在一个新连接中
let's say on a new connection
首先在一个新连接上仍然是0x30 0x13
so first of all on a new connection still hex 30 Hex 13
如果我们额外malloc一个
if we do an additional allocation
malloc 2，然后free 2
malloc 2 and then free 2
仍然是0x30 0x13
still Hex 30 Hex 13
按理说应是一个不同的地址
this should be a different tcache address
脱离剧本讲是这样的
this is what happens when we go off a
好吧，我先暂停，搞清楚怎么回事
all right I need to figure out what is going on  rather than keeping you waiting
我马上回来
I'll be right back
我回来了
I'm back okay
搞清楚了，我去
I figured out what was going on oh man
messages和所有这些都是全局变量
so the messages and all of this they're stored globally
所以每当我重连时
so when I was reconnecting
message数组的初始状态都是有数据的
I was starting off with a state of that message buffer
和我期望的不一样
that was not what I was expecting
这是ult的源码
here is the source code of that ult
哎呦
whoops
在新连接中，这些不是我期望的0
this was not null like I was expecting it on a new connection
要注意这些长期运行的多线程服务
keep in mind with these long running threading services
它们的内部状态可能会一直有效
the internal state might persist
既是好事也是坏事
this is a good thing and a bad thing
好的原因是，作为攻击者可以泄漏其中的一部分
it is a good thing because as an attacker you can leak parts of it
或修改一部分，然后一步一步完成利用
set things up and then actually do step by step exploitation
对攻击者不好的一面是
as a bad thing as an attacker
因为你可能会忘记，会搞混
is because you can forget and get mixed up
为了解决这个问题
alright so to fix that
我现在在pwntools脚本中启动它
I'm now launching it in my pwntools script
当你对一个网络上的服务这么做时
when you do this for a service that listens on a network
确保事后清理干净
make sure to clean it up afterwards
你可以这么做
you can do this
或者可以用pwntools的context实现
or you can have pwntools do it for you using a context
所以不管发生什么
so no matter what happens
它总是会清理这个进程
it'll now always clean up that process
好，我们启动这个进程
all right so we run that process
接入
we connect to it
然后malloc 2次，free 2次
and then we do 2 allocations 2 frees
再malloc 1次，输出它
and then we do an allocation and print it out
这是tcache next指针的最后2字节，0x20 0x0f
that is the last two bytes hex 20 hex 0f of the tcache forward pointer
当然我们可以多malloc free 一次
of course we can do free another malloc and free
现在这是next指针的最后2字节，0x30和0x13
now these are the forward last two bytes hex 30 and hex 13
用0x1330-0x0f20，它应该在0x400左右
if you subtract this it should be somewhere around hex 400
因为我们每次分配1024字节（0x400）
because we're allocating 1024 bytes per allocation
是0x410，因为包括了元数据
hex 410 including the metadata all right
提醒一下，我们本来是要做这个竞争的
so as a reminder we were going to do this race
我们开始竞争吧
so let's do this race
我们在一个线程循环malloc内存，写入数据，释放内存
so we're going to allocate write data into it  and deallocate in one thread in a loop
在另一个线程中，输出这个内存
and in another thread we'll just print out that allocation
最终会这样
eventually this will happen
我们会输入数据
we'll input the data
打印它
we'll trigger the printf
竞争将会发生
the race will happen
当printf算出长度后
so that the length is calculated
但在要写入到标准输出时
but by the time the write happens
这个内存已经被释放了
that allocation has been freed
这个内存中的数据被换成了，什么来着，tcache元数据
and that location has been replaced by what's it called a tcache metadata
我们启动它
we launch it
我们要用我们的
we're going to use our
当然，你可以更合理地使用多进程
of course you can use multi processing properly
我们不会那样做
we're not going to do that
我们建立两个连接
we're gonna make two connections
我们要
and in one connection we're going to
我们要fork
we're gonna fork the interpreter
在子进程中
if the result of the fork is the child
我们要循环
we're going to in a loop
当然这样输出会很乱
and of course this will be messy and
好吧，写的好一点
well I'll just do it more properly
循环1000次
say 1000 times
我们发送malloc 0 scanf 0
we're going to send the line malloc 0 scanf 0
你想要输出多长的数据
how much do you want to
假设要的是next指针和tcache_perthread_struct指针（key）
let's say if you want the two keywords the next pointer and the per thread struct pointer
输入AAAAAAAABBBBBBBB
AAAAAAAABBBBBBBB
然后我们free 0
and then we want to printf 0 no sorry and then we want to free 0
在另一个线程中，我们一直printf
and in another thread we want to printf all the time
希望printf会从这里开始运行
and the printf will hopefully start running right here
但是不，不好意思
but  no sorry
我们在这里printf
we want printf here
然后在另一个线程中free
then we want the free in another thread
其实我觉得这不重要
actually don't think it matters
因为是竞争嘛
because of the way the race happens
但我们先这么做
but this what we're going to do
然后我们
and then in the and then we'll
记得清理干净
remember to clean up
好吧
okay
稍等
wait
我应该取TID的
I should get TID
哦，我可以得到pid
oh I can get pid
哦，没问题，这是fork
oh no this is forking
然后在父进程中
okay and then in the parent
我们将
we will
这是就是父进程，所以不用else了
well this is the parent so
在父进程中，我们不会干等着
in the parent we will instead sit there
在另一个线程中free 0
and in the other thread free 0
好吧
all right
然后
and then
我们要看一下输出结果
we're going to see what comes out from these prints
好的
boom
能看到有一大堆AAAA BBBB
alright so you can see we have a bunch of AAAA BBBB
也有一堆NONE
we also have a bunch of NONE
看起来像
where it looks like we
是这样的，free执行在了scanf之后，printf之前
what happened was that the free happened between the scanf and the printf
我想我们在这里free 0，可能会更好
actually I think we'll have better luck if we do free 0 here
然后在这里printf 0
and  printf 0 here
好
okay
好像崩溃了
think it crashed
哦
ops
什么情况
what is going on
为啥什么都没打印
why wasn't printing anything
好吧
okay
哦，它打印了
oh it was printing
在这
this is all again
好吧，好吧，没事
okay okay cool
所以我们需要打印的是r2的输出
so now we need to read of this second thread
我们用malloc scanf free
so we're doing malloc scanf free
然后在另一个线程printf
and then we're doing printf
我们希望在这里切换到printf
we're hoping to hit the printf right here
这样它会在free后再write
so it write during the free
这样它先解析出字符串的长度，然后free执行了
so that it first  calculates the string then the free happens
最后输出
and then it prints it out
好了
so here it is again
我们没竞争成功
we didn't win the race there
可能循环次数还不够
this might just be not be enough
如果分成几行，我们可以更容易地打印出来
we can actually print this out easier if we split into lines
再用set去重
and then just compute the set of unique ones
结果出来了
and here it is
这是我们得到的所有东西
so here is all of the things that we got
有MESSAGE: AAAAAAA
we got message aaaaa
有点奇怪
that's a weird one
所以这里可能是
so probably or possibly what's happening here is
在strlen的时候
during the strlen the
好吧，没想到一个好的原因
yeah this one I don't have a good explanation for it
这条message是我们想要的
here we have a message are the exact thing we're looking for which is
strlen解析出长度是16字节
we have we did the strlen of 16 bytes
然后输出了16字节
and then we wrote out 16 bytes
当然，第一个QWORD（8字节）是null
then of course the first QWORD is null
因为这是第一个free的（next为null）
because that's the first allocation that was freed
tcache中在他面前什么也没有
there's nothing in tcache before him
另一个qword是一个指向线程arena的指针
and then the next one is a pointer to somewhere inside the tcache arena
tcache_perthread_struct存储在该arena
the tcache perthread_struct lives in that tcache arena
在吗？
does it
不，它应该在进程的线程本地存储中
no this should be in the thread local storage of the process
还有一个消息，和这个略微不同
we have other garbage another thing with a slightly different
它看起来像指针，DCS 7f
it looks like pointer DCS 7f
由于某种原因，这只打印了15字节而不是16字节
oh yeah this only printed 15 instead of 16 bytes for some reason
但我们已经可以泄露了
but we have our leak
我们试着和ppt匹配一下
so I would say let's do this matches closer to the slides
如果我们malloc scanf printf
if we do malloc scanf printf
然后在另一个线程中free
then we do the free in the other one
哦，对了，该输出 r1的
oh and then we read r1
哦，这行不通
oh but that doesn't work
我应该调整一下幻灯片
I should actually adjust the slides
就应该在一个循环中malloc scanf free
because this is the way to do it malloc scanf free in a loop
这样做才有意义
doing stuff that that makes sense
然后我们希望能在这两者之间进行打印
and then the printf we hope to get running right between there
好吧
boom all right
现在我们泄露出了
so now we have leaked out
指向线程tcache_perthread_struct对象的指针
a pointer somewhere in memory to the tcache per thread struct of that thread
这是件大事，非常令人兴奋
right this is huge and very exciting
顺便说一下，我认为它在arena中
I actually do think that this is allocated in the memory space of that arena by the way
现在我们有了线程特定的arena的地址
and now we have a thread specific arena address
很酷
very awesome
接下来，我们将讨论如何利用这个地址
so moving on we'll talk about what we'll do with that address
既然现在我们知道内存中的某个东西在哪里了
now that we know where something in memory is
我们就可以开始尝试重叠chunk和各种好东西了
of course now we can start overlapping allocations and all sorts of good stuff
因为我们知道要在哪里重叠了
because we know where to overlap them into
请继续关注
stay tuned